MISSION 44 "IT'S JUST THE ARRIVAL OF WINTER."
（任务44 冬天到来）
-DING! -FLINCH
-叮咚！ -（吓到）
CRASH
（撞到）
TREMBLE
（颤抖）
SHE HIT HER FOREHEAD.
（撞到额头了）
ONE NEW MESSAGE
（有一则新讯息）
MAID CAFE ITAN WAS A HUGE SUCCESS! FOR KOMI
（伊旦女仆咖啡厅大获成功！ 古见同学）
FROM: NAJIMI OSANA BRING THE NOTEBOOK I ASKED YOU TO PREPARE.
（长名驯染：可以请你带 上次拜托的笔记本来吗？）
NUMBER 4 OCTOBER TO NOVEMBER
（《第四册 10月到11月》）
HOW TO COMMUNICATE EVEN MONKEYS CAN TALK
（《传达方式的法则》 《猴子也会的谈话技巧》）
KOMI
（古见）
-ICY TOUCH -FLINCH
（冰冷 吓到）
Hey-ho, Komi!
早安 哈啰 古见同学！
FIDGET
（跃跃欲试）
-Good morning Ko… -STARTLE
-早安 -（惊吓）
Oh, yeah.
早啊
When a person has extreme social anxiety,
所谓的“交流障碍症” 是指不擅长和人交流的一种症状
they struggle to communicate with others.
或是指有这种症状的人
Bear in mind…
不过需要注意的是…
NERVOUS
（紧张）
Hm?
怎么了？
What's up with Komi?
古见同学怎么了啊？
Did something happen?
有什么事吗？
-ICY TOUCH -FLINCH
（紧贴 冰冷）
Bear in mind.
需要注意的是…
They only struggle to form connections.
这些人只是不擅长社交
It doesn't mean they don't want to.
但并不表示他们不想和别人有往来
However…
然而…
Komi still doesn't know.
古见同学还不知道
She doesn't know the harsh fate that awaits her.
等待着她的未来有多么残酷
This well-known hellscape, Itan Private High School.
没错 这里就是人尽皆知的魔境 私立伊旦高中
Though it's a famous high school, entrance is based on interviews only.
纵使是县内少数的升学高中 但是否能入学只靠面试决定
To pass, students must be unique.
该校的入学合格基准是个性
In other words…
也就是说…
freaks,
奇人
weirdos,
怪人
loners,
边缘人
miscreants…
异端者
and eccentrics fill the school.
是一堆个性独特的人聚集的学校
Great rivals.
阻挡在前的强敌
-Tender moments. -YAMAI IS OBSESSED
-擦肩而过的青春 -（山井同学是病娇）
But can our heroine survive this battlefield?
她是否能从这战场存活下来？
Do it! 100 friends!
目标是交100个朋友
Do it! Be a master of communication!
立志成为沟通大师！
What fate will befall Komi?
古见同学的命运将会何去何从？
What are you doing?
你在做什么啊？
Yeah! Anyway, Komi. Did you bring it?
所以说呢 古见同学 带那个来了吗？
I sent you a message this morning. You know!
我早上传讯息给你了吧？ 就是那个啊！
NUMBER 4 OCTOBER TO NOVEMBER
（《10月到11月》）
Oh, great!
太好了！
What's that?
那是什么？
The people these past six months who…
这半年一起玩过的人…
-Never mind. -Huh?
-算了 -什么？
We'll use this to make…
以这个为基础…
-Ta-da! Komi's Book of Friends! -JUST A MEMO PAD
完成了！《古见友人账》！
Isn't that a copyright violation?
这名字不会有问题吗？
The rules are simple!
规则很简单
Give it to your friends and they write their names!
只要将这本友人账 拿给朋友签名就好
But why?
为什么？
Why not!
又没关系！
It'll be like a nature guide! It's fun!
就像某某图鉴一样 很好玩啊！
Here, Komi!
来吧 古见同学！
KOMI'S BOOK OF FRIENDS
（《古见友人账》）
HITOHITO TADANO NAJIMI OSANA
（只野仁人 长名驯染）
HIGH FIVE
（没击到掌）
HIMIKO AGARI
（上理卑美子）
REN YAMAI
（山井恋）
RUMBLE
（隆隆声）
MAKERU YADANO
（矢田野真华留）
GLANCE
（偷瞄）
OMOHARU NAKANAKA
（中中思春）
-STARE -STARTLE
（隆隆声）
AKAKO ONIGASHIMA HIMEKO KISHI
（鬼岛朱子 岸姬子）
SHIGEO CHIARAI, TAISEI SONODA MONO SHINOBINO
（地洗井茂夫 园田大势、忍野裳乃）
NENE ONEMINE
（尾根峰宁宁）
KAEDE OTORI
（尾鸡枫）
TADANO, NAJIMI, AGARI, YAMAI, YADANO, NAKANAKA, ONIGASHIMA
（只野、驯染、上理、山井 矢田野、中中、岸）
KISHI, CHIARAI, SONODA, SHINOBINO, ONEMINE, OTORI
（鬼岛、地洗井、园田 忍野、尾根峰、尾鸡）
"AO 100 SHOKU"
（《阿欧哈苦秀苦》）
Done already?
写完了？
-NOT TRYING TO BE MEAN -To reach 100 she needs 87 more.
-（没有恶意） -距离交100个朋友 还剩87人
TREMBLE
（颤抖）
-It's already been six months. -THAT'S PRETTY SLOW.
-都过半年了吧？ -（按这步调很难做到吧）
MISSION 45 "IT'S JUST A DELINQUENT."
（任务45 不良少年）
My name is Makoto Katai.
我的名字叫片居诚
I'm a regular high schooler.
是个普通的高中男生
My favorite food is Hamburg steak.
喜欢的食物是汉堡排
My least favorite is green peppers.
讨厌的食物是青椒
I'm a late bloomer, and kind of shy.
我有点晚熟 不敢向人搭话
I'm not good at taking the initiative.
也不擅长自己主动行动
But I'm a normal high schooler.
但我算是个普通的高中男生
IS KATAI A THUG?
（片居同学是硬派男子吗？）
STAFF ROOM
（教职员办公室）
That was nerve-wracking…
我好紧张
I was so nervous asking where my class is!
要去问自己是哪个班级的 让我超紧张的！
-It started six months ago. -SIX MONTHS AGO
那是半年前的事了
The first day of school.
那天是入学典礼
I had caught a cold and spent a week in bed.
我得了感冒 躺了一个礼拜
I didn't attend the first week of class.
开学第一周没去上学
-It was hard to go, even after recovering. -HE DID COME TO THE GATE
-就算康复了也不太敢去学校 -（来到过校门口）
I'll go tomorrow.
我总想着
Tomorrow I'll go to school…
“明天要去上学”
is what I told myself.
一直这么想着
-And now look at the season! -THUNK
-就到这个季节了！ -（撞）
Early winter.
已是初冬
But over summer break, I changed!
但是我在暑假期间已经改变了
-I started working out. -500 more! You can do it!
-觉得这样下去不行 锻炼了身体 -再500下 努力点！
I dyed my hair too, to keep the bullies away.
为了避免被欺负 我还染了头发
I don't look like a dropout at all!
我怎么看都不像不上学的阴沉家伙！
I'm just…
我是普通人
Just a normal high schooler!
我是个普通的男高中生！
Alright. Here I go!
很好 进去吧！
I can't. I'm so nervous!
不行 我还是好紧张！
-He's looking in our class! -Scary!
-不良少年在偷看我们班 -讨厌 好吓人！
No. It's fine.
不 没事的
Today's the day I…
我今天一定要…
THUD
（撞）
OUCH
（很痛）
He kicked the door…
他踹门？
Who could that be?
他是谁？
What's his deal?
究竟怎么了？
-VERY, VERY NERVOUS. -He's angry!
-（非常紧张） -他在生气！
LEER
（微笑）
TADANO'S PERSPECTIVE
（只野同学的视角）
Oh no.
糟糕了
I forgot to ask where my desk is.
我忘记问自己坐哪里了
I don't want to wait up front. I'll go to the back.
站在前面等太显眼了 不想那样 我到后面去吧
I'll wait for the teacher here.
就在这里等老师来好了
Everyone's looking at me.
天啊 大家都在看我
-Oh! I should smile! -LEER
-对了 要保持微笑！ -（微笑）
-TADANO FIGURED HIM OUT. -So that's what he's thinking!
-（只野同学察觉到了） -原来他是这种类型的啊！
What's his deal?
那个人是怎样啦？
Someone talk to him!
谁快去跟他搭话！
-Hey-ho! -Huh?
-早安 哈啰！ -什么？
Oh! Katai?
等等 是阿片啊？
-Long time no see! -Our savior!
-好久不见了！ -救世主驯染登场！
-Najimi knows everyone. -When did I see you last?
-驯染跟全校学生都是儿时玩伴 -上次见面是何时啊？过得好吗？
Anyway, besides that.
话说回来
You've really cha-- Gurk!
感觉你变得不一样…
I can't have everyone knowing about my past.
不能让大家知道我的过去
I have to explain to Najimi.
我得和驯染同学好好说明
Najimi!
驯染！
QUIETLY
（安静经过）
Oh. Gotta smile!
对了 差点忘了微笑！
N-Najimi!
驯染！
Najimi went to the restroom.
驯染只是去上厕所
-I wonder if someone will talk to me? -FIDGET
-快点来跟我说话吧 -（内心躁动）
Huh?
奇怪
SWARM
（聚集）
Everyone's gathered in one spot.
大家好像都聚集在一个地方
I guess she's a popular student.
是班上受欢迎的学生吗？
We must protect Komi at all costs!
我们至少要死守住古见同学！
Save her…
请拯救她
Divine intervention…
保佑我们吧
I've got to change.
我要改变自己
I'll go talk to them!
鼓起勇气 去跟他们搭话吧！
Yikes! He's coming!
糟糕 他过来了！
-She's done for. -Someone save her!
-完蛋了！ -请保佑我们！
We'll protect Komi!
我们来保护古见同学！
You guys are…
你们是…
-The class delinquents! -Huh?
-班上的不良少年！ -什么？
BUMP
（撞）
-Day… desk? -(GOOD) DAY (WHERE'S MY) DESK?
-你…事吧？ -（你没事吧？）
Die? Death?
“死”？“你死吧”？
I got phlegm in my throat.
痰卡在喉咙
Did they understand?
他能听懂吗？
They did not.
并没有
-Useless! -They're not real delinquents!
-没用的东西！ -你们真的是不良少年吗？
Oh good. They seem alright.
太好了 似乎传达到了
Now, who were they standing around?
先不说这个 大家到底围着谁呢？
I…
好…
I'm scared!
好可怕！
-TREMBLE -WHY?
（颤抖 为什么？）
W-What is this pressure I'm feeling?
有股好强烈的压迫感！
She's looking! At me!
她在看我 直盯着我看！
Why is she staring so much?
她干吗一直看我啊？
I'm scared!
人家好怕！
My knees are weak.
我的腿没力了！
He sat down!
他坐下了！
Deep breaths, deep breaths!
我要深呼吸才行！
EXHALE
（吐气）
-She's still staring! -TOO SCARED TO MOVE
-她还在看我！ -（怕到动弹不得）
Everyone usually looks away when I meet their gaze.
明明其他人跟我对到眼 都会移开视线！
But this might be the first time someone looked me in the eyes.
不过这好像是我今天 第一次看着别人的眼睛
Oh, right!
对了！
Even Monkeys Can Talk chapter 4, page 116!
《猴子也会的谈话技巧》 第4章116页有说
"Get your feelings across by looking people in the eyes!"
“要看着对方的眼睛说话 以便传达自己的心情”
That's why this person is looking me in the eyes!
难怪她会看着我的眼睛
It means she wants to communicate, right?
这代表她想跟我好好交谈吧？
Okay! I can do it too!
好 我也要回应她！
-They're glaring at each other. -It's a stare-down!
-他们在瞪对方！ -这就是互相瞪眼直视！
SCARED
（害怕）
TREMBLE
（颤抖）
Uh.
啊
Um, you're Katai. Aren't you?
请问你是片居同学吧？
Huh?
什么？
Aaah! No!
天啊 糟糕！
My voice changed and now it's super low.
我过变声期后声音很低！
If I don't make it higher, I sound like I'm really mad!
不刻意拉高声音的话 听起来感觉会超不爽的！
Now he thinks I'm a jerk.
他会不会觉得我很讨人厌？
You were out of school for a long time, right?
你之前都请假对吧？
If you want, I can show you around!
若不介意的话 我带你认识学校如何？
Huh?
什么？
I'd… like that.
那就麻烦你了
This is the music room.
这里是音乐教室
W-Wow.
好厉害！
-This is the power of eye contact. -STARE
-这就是眼神交流的力量 -（盯着看）
-Here is the library. -LIBRARY
-这里是图书室 -（图书室）
Walking through the school, just the two of us.
我竟然跟他单独走在校园！
We're like real friends!
我们就像朋友一样！
-GRIN -SQUEAL
（微笑 尖叫）
Are you listening?
你在听吗？
Oh yeah!
我知道了！
She was staring in order to tell me.
她之所以盯着我看 就是想告诉我这件事
The Master of Communication.
她是沟通大师
She's Commu, the Master of Communication!
她是善于交际的沟通大师 善交际同学！
Go get 'em!
好好加油！
Commu?
“善交际同学”？
COMMU
（善交际同学）
-Bang! -COMMUNICATION SKILLS
-砰！ -（沟通能力）
MISSION 46 "IT'S JUST STUDYING AT NAKANAKA'S."
（任务46 在中中同学家念书）
That's all everyone. See you tomorrow.
辛苦了 明天见
Let's go out for ramen.
去车站前的拉面店吧
Sounds good!
好主意！
-It's winter! -A SNOWMAN POSE
-冬天到了！ -（雪人的姿势！）
Maybe I just won't ask.
这里就不刻意吐槽了
I thought you hated winter.
等等 我记得你不是讨厌冬天吗？
I can't stand the cold.
我讨厌冷天气
But there are lots of fun winter events.
但是冬天也有很多愉快的活动
Christmas, gift money, skiing, cozy rooms, the Ekiden race! And…
圣诞节、压岁钱、滑雪、暖桌 驿站接力赛 然后还有…
Term finals!
期末考试！
-Tests. You're always the same. -TERM FINALS
-考试 你总是这样 -（期末考试）
Standing between me and my fun.
偏偏挡在我期待的事前妨碍我
How dare you!
我饶不了你！
Oh yeah! We can study at Nakanaka's house!
对了 去小中中家念书就好了！
They just want to play games.
这家伙只想着要玩游戏！
NAKANAKA RESIDENCE
（中中家）
Anyway… You are welcome at my castle.
所以你们要来我的城堡是无妨
But what's up with her?
但那家伙来干吗？
Who's she talking about? We don't know, do we Komi?
你是说谁呀？真搞不懂耶 对吧？古见同学
It's you! You!
我是说你这家伙！
Why? We're friends aren't we, Nakanaka?
干吗这样说啦？小中中 我们不是朋友吗？
Forgetting me and inviting Komi? Unacceptable!
把我丢在一旁 邀古见同学回家 太扯了！
I don't remember being friends with you.
我可不记得有你这种朋友
You're just jealous that Komi came over.
你只是羡慕古见同学来我的城堡吧
You harlot!
你这放荡的女人！
RUMBLE
（发怒）
These two are not very compatible.
难道她们俩个性不合吗？
Thanks for having me!
打扰了！
Good night!
大家晚安！
Asleep!
睡着了！
What was the point of this visit?
这家伙到底来干吗的？
So, Komi.
那古见同学
Sit next to me.
你就坐我旁边吧
There's a physics formula I don't understand..
物理有个公式我不太懂
N-No! You should sit here.
不行 你应该坐这边！
That cushion is of poor quality!
那边的坐垫质量不好！
This is how Yamai and Nakanaka
于是山井同学 与中中同学便开始针对
sparked off their battle for Komi's heart.
“古见同学比较喜欢谁？”进行比赛
WILD GIRLS BEAST EARS, THE MOVIE
（《野生少女 兽耳女孩电影版》）
I know, Komi! Want to play a game?
对了 古见同学 要玩游戏吗？
Last time was hard, right?
上次玩的有点难吧？
I've gathered some games with easier controls.
后来我收集了一些 操作容易的游戏哦
Nakanaka's attack: "For Komi's Benefit."
中中同学展开攻击 “我是为了古见同学着想”
I thought we came to study…
我们应该是来念书的啊
Of course she doesn't want to play.
谁要玩游戏啊
-That's such a boyish activity. -HEH
-又不是臭男生 -（嘲笑）
-What? -But it was blocked!
-什么？ -但攻击被挡下来了
Girls like romance!
女生就该聊恋爱话题！
Komi, who's your crush?
我问你 古见同学喜欢的人是谁啊？
Mine is you.
我喜欢你哦
"Practically a Confession!"
“几乎算是告白”
YAMAI'S ATTACK: PRACTICALLY A CONFESSION!
（山井同学展开攻击！ “几乎算是告白！”）
It's not very effective…
但似乎效果薄弱
Um, what about studying?
请问还要不要念书啊？
That reminds me…
这么说来…
I noticed when I entered this room.
一进到这房间我就在想了
The whole interior is black and you have so many anime and movie posters.
摆设几乎都是黑色的 墙上贴满动漫跟电影的海报
It's like an otaku boy's room.
跟宅男的房间一样呢！
It's super effective!
“攻击效果显著！”
Alright then.
那你倒说说看
What do you consider a girly room?
怎么样才像女生的房间
That's easy.
这还用说嘛
You need a big mirror.
要有一面能照自己的镜子
Make-up, perfume, pink items, antique-style furniture.
还要有化妆品、香水 粉红色小物、古典风的家具
And serve jasmine tea, not barley…
用茉莉茶招待客人 而不是麦茶…
How basic.
跟风仔
It's super effective!
“攻击效果显著！”
Your nails are filthy! I'm not interested in your opinion.
连指甲都没保养好的人没资格说我
You're the one with damaged hair!
你的发质才严重受损
Since you change the color often.
谁叫你动不动就染头发
You live at home, so I bet you can't even cook!
你住老家 应该也不会做菜吧
So unfeminine.
贤惠度真够低
-Femininity! -GIRLS ARE SCARY.
-贤惠？ -（女生真可怕）
Don't judge me on something you can't even quantify!
不要用无法数值化的东西 来分优劣好吗？
According to our star charts, I'm a better match for Komi!
算命结果说古见同学跟我比较相配！
There you go being basic again!
跟风发言又出现了！
There's no evidence!
你有证据吗？
Why do you talk like that?
你不觉得你讲话方式很怪吗？
You do it because you're an internet addict, right?
我知道了 你沉迷于上网 说话才都这个语调对吧？
You're as good at finding information as my mom!
什么啦？你收集情报的能力 跟妈妈有得拼
-How old did you say you were? -Komi is…
-对了 你今年贵庚啊？ -古见同学她…
-Let's calm down… -Huh?!
-先冷静一下… -什么？
Oh, nothing.
没事
Komi, which of us is a better friend?
古见同学 我们两个 谁才是你重要的朋友？
And now the spears point at Komi.
矛头终于转向古见同学
YOU'RE BOTH IMPORTANT TO ME.
（你们两人都是我重要的朋友）
-SECRETLY HAPPY -FIDGETY
（还蛮高兴的两人 害羞 扭捏）
Y-Yeah, but!
可是…
If you had to choose, who would it be?
硬要分高下的话 你会怎么选？
Why not see who gets a higher test score?
那用考试成绩来决定如何…
Shut up.
你闭嘴
They're in perfect sync.
这两人好有默契啊
We can't keep asking Komi.
不能再逼问古见同学了
She'll hate me if I'm aggressive.
太咄咄逼人会被讨厌
Have you ever not been aggressive?
你有哪次不咄咄逼人？
Isn't there something? Some way to settle this?
就没有什么能分胜负的东西吗？
Games.
游戏
We have video games!
我们还有游戏！
Yeah.
好
Let's do it!
好 来吧
-Games! -Me too!
-来玩游戏！ -我也要玩！
Hang on! Don't put a banana there!
可恶 你别在那边放香蕉！
-I'll let my strategy speak for itself! -Yes, that's it!
-战略就是一切 战略最重要！ -没错！
Scoundrel! You're aiming that red carapace at me!
臭家伙 不要一直用红龟壳丢我！
Must be your imagination!
-很好 -那是你的错觉吧？
Take that!
吃我这招！
The R button on the right…
-你那样是在干吗？ -右手的这个R钮…
Take that! And that!
接招！可恶！
Boom!
爆炸吧！
Finish!
结束！
Yay! I win!
好耶！我赢了！
That means Komi's best friend is me!
跟古见同学最要好的朋友就是我！
BANG
（撞）
Najimi, why do you have to be like that?
驯染 你这人就是这样
They competed on their tests too.
最后也用考试的方式决胜负了
A draw?!
同分？
You've all cleared your desks, right?
抽屉里都清空了吗？
You've got your writing tools?
文具都拿出来了吗？
If you drop anything I'll get it, so let me know.
掉地上就告诉老师 我会去捡
Now, start!
那开始考试！
WOBBLE
（摇晃）
POP
（抽出）
Komi only prepared two pencils.
古见同学只拿出两支铅笔
HAS TO SAY SHE DROPPED HER PENCIL…
（必须跟老师说铅笔掉了！）
Komi is too shy about standing out so she can't say it.
但是太引人注目 不敢说出口的古见同学
Huh? Komi's…
怎么了？古见同学…
not writing…?
她还没写？
PLOP
（掉落）
Oh, I get it.
原来是这样
Around there.
应该是这附近吧
Teacher? I dropped my mechanical pencil.
老师 我的自动笔掉了
-Huh? -Uh, sorry.
-什么？ -不好意思
Could you get it for me?
可以帮我捡吗？
Sure.
好
Hm? Is this yours, Komi?
奇怪 这是古见的吗？
You're the only one in this class who uses a pencil, after all. Here.
班上也只有你会用铅笔吧 拿去
All set.
这样就好了
-Here. -Oh, thank you.
-拿去 -谢谢老师
JAPANESE HISTORY TERM FINAL CLASS 1-1, HITOHITO TADANO
（日本史 学期末范围 只野仁人）
Komi's so clumsy.
古见同学真是冒失呢
Huh?
奇怪
Wait, what?
等等 什么？
CLUMSY
（冒失）
I forgot to get my eraser out!
我忘了拿橡皮擦出来
I CAN'T MAKE ANY MISTAKES!
（这下不能写错了！）
Excuse me!
不好意思！
I dropped my eraser.
我的橡皮擦掉了
Again?
又来了？
I'm sorry.
非常抱歉
Here.
拿去
Thank you very much.
谢谢老师
Is this alright?
这样应该没关系吧
Neither of them could focus on the test.
结果两人都无法专心考试
BONUS SCENE
（片尾彩蛋）
Huh?
奇怪
Hey, lend me your eraser.
哥哥 借我橡皮擦
No.
不要
Huh? Why?
什么？为什么不行？
The eraser became a family heirloom.
成了传家宝的橡皮擦
Subtitle translation by: Claire Tanaka
字幕翻译：吴敬美